<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    
    <info>
        <title>OESS Frontend</title>
        <releaseinfo role="outdated">1.0.0</releaseinfo>
        <author>
            <orgname>IU GlobalNOC</orgname>
            <uri type="website">
                <link xlink:href="http://globalnoc.iu.edu">http://globalnoc.iu.edu</link>
            </uri>
            <address>
            <street>2711 E 10th Street</street>
            <city>Bloomington, IN</city>
            <postcode>47408</postcode>
            <country>USA</country>
        </address>
            <email>syseng@GlobalNOC.iu.edu</email>
        </author>
    </info>   

    <chapter>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
            The OESS frontend is designed to be an easy to use and intuitive point and click interface
            to creating and removing dynamic circuits on Openflow enabled switches. It is broken out
            into two main sections - the user interface and the admin interface - both of which are
            explained in detail in the following sections. This guide is primarily intended as a jumping off
            point for people that are new to using OESS and will cover initial set up as well as explaining
            the steps along the process of creating a circuit.

        </para>
    </chapter>      
    
    
    <chapter>
        <title>Getting Started</title>    
        <para> 
            This guide assumes that you have successfully installed the software and started the
            relevant services. If this is not the case, please refer to the included QUICK_START
            and/or README files in the code distribution for assistance. When visiting the frontend
            for the first time you should be presented with a page like the following.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>                
                     <imagedata fileref="images/oess_workgroups.png" width="400" />
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>        
        </para>
        
        <para>          
            This is the entry point to the user interface. At this point, there's not a whole lot you can do here.
            First we will need to visit the admin interface to configure users, workgroups, and to tell
            OESS about our network. In a typical install, the admin section is located at &lt;url_base&gt;/admin/admin_index.cgi
            and will have the username and password provided during the setup script.                    
        </para>       
        
    </chapter>
    
    <chapter>       
        <title>Admin Interface</title>
        <para> 
            When first visiting the admin interface it should look something like this. 
        </para>
        <para>
            <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/oess_admin.png" width="400"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
        </para>
        
        <sect1>
            <title>Discovery</title>
   
            <para>
                Discovery is the process through which OESS learns about the network automatically. Any
                Openflow device that is configured to use the OESS host as its controller should automatically
                be picked up. When OESS discovers a new node or link, the software puts it into a "Pending Confirmation"
                state. A user with access to the admin interface can then go and confirm that this
                node is available to the software and set its relevant information. 
            </para>
   
            <para>
                If you have already configured your Openflow devices to be talking to the OESS host, you should see 
                that the OESS software has discovered them. When a node is detected it will attempt to do a DNS 
                lookup to determine the name for you automatically, but if that does not succeed or you simply
                would prefer a different name you can change it while confirming. The geographic coordinates
                are only important as to where it will show up on the interactive map.                
            </para>
            <para>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                     <imageobject>
                         <imagedata fileref="images/oess_admin_confirm_node.png" width="400"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
                                
            </para>
                        
            <para>
                Once two or more nodes have been confirmed, OESS will attempt to discover links between them.
                When these are discovered they will appear in the table below nodes and will also be
                waiting for confirmation. The name for a link is only to be useful to humans.                                
            </para>
            
        </sect1>
        
        <sect1>
            <title>Network</title>

            <para>
                The Network section shows the interactive map of all currently active devices and
                links in your network. By clicking any of these we can adjust their properties such
                as name, geographic coordinates, or decommission it from the network.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/oess_admin_network.png" width="400"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
                
            </para>
            
            <para>
                *IMPORTANT* If you have registered your topology with a remote
                Topology service and rename or decommission a node or link, you will have to
                resubmit the topology to update the service or OESS will not understand a request
                coming in with the old name. 
            </para>

        </sect1>
        
        <sect1>
            <title>Remote Links</title>            
            <para>
                The Remote Links section allows you to configure which parts of your network have connections to other
                networks. It also allows you to submit your network's topology to the remote topology service
                configured during the setup script. If you are not planning on using interdomain aspects you can ignore this section.
            </para>
            
            <para> 
                To configure a remote link, simply click the New Remote Link button. A popup will
                appear showing you the current active network. Choose which endpoint on your network
                has the connection to the remote network. A list of interfaces on that node should
                appear next to the map. Choose which interface has the connection to the other
                network and you will be prompted to enter the information for this remote link. 
                
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/oess_admin_add_remote_link.png" width="400"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
            </para>
            
            <para>
                The remote URN is in the form "urn:ogf:network:domain=foo:node=bar:port=biz:link=bam" and must match what the other network
                has configured as identifying this link. The name is the name of this link and what the other network will use in their topology to 
                identify you in the "link=bam" part of their URN.
            </para>
        
            <para>
                Once you are in a position where you are satisfied with the topology, you can click the "Submit Topology" button to upload your topology
                to the server you configured during the setup script.
            </para>
                       
        
        </sect1>
        
        <sect1>
            <title>Remote Devices</title>
            <para>
                The Remote Devices section allows you to configure geographical coordinates for devices in other networks that have been imported.
                The sole purpose of this is to make the interactive maps more useful and realistic when dealing with remote nodes. If you are not using
                interdomain aspects of the software you can ignore this section.
            </para>
            
            <para> 
                To set a latitude and longitude for a remote device, simply click the
                corresponding row and enter the desired values in the popup.                 
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/oess_admin_remote_devices.png" width="400"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
            
            </para>
        </sect1> 
        
        <sect1>
            <title>Users</title>
            <para>
                The Users section lets you configure what users are known in the system. Before a person can use the software they must have a 
                user entry in this section. There are two special users: 
                <table>                    
                    <title>Special Users</title>                    
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>System</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    The user that the internal software uses when scheduling actions and doing interprocess communication.
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>OSCARS</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    Not included by default, needs to be added if you are going to be using interdomain. 
                                    The user that all remote initiated provisioning actions will use.
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </para>
            
            <para> 
                To add a new user, click the "New User" button. To edit an existing user, select
                their name from the list. The process for adding or editting a user is the same.
                Fill out the popup provided with the information for the user and click "Save". The
                "Username(s)" field should be filled out with the username that the user will log in
                with through whatever security layer is used at the Apache level (basic auth, single
                sign on, kerb auth, etc). This is basically what the REMOTE_USER environment
                variable will be set to. If desired, multiple usernames can be associated to a
                single user account by separating each with a comma. This is to allow, for example,
                authentication mechanisms such as OpenID if so desired.                 
            </para>

            <para>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/oess_admin_users.png" width="400"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
                
            </para>
          
        </sect1>
        
        <sect1>
            <title>Workgroups</title>
            <para>
                Workgroups are groups of users with access to a certain subset of the local network. For a user to be able
                to do anything with OESS, they must be associated to at least one workgroup. In a new installation there will be
                no workgroups so one will have to be created.                
            </para>
            
            <para>
                To create a new workgroup, simply click the "New Workgroup" button, choose a name for it, and click "Save". The name, excluding
                the one special workgroup mentioned below, serves the sole purpose of identifying it to humans.
            </para>
            
            <para> 
                To edit a workgroup, select it from the list presented. At this point you will be
                presented with a table of users in the workgroup as well as a listing of which edge
                ports they are allowed to create circuits to and from. From here you can add users
                to the workgroup by clicking the "Add User to Workgroup" button and selecting the
                desired users from the table provided or remove them by clicking the "Remove" link
                next to their name. You can also add and remove allowed edge ports in a similar
                fashion. When adding an edge port, first click the node on the map, then select the
                port from the table of options. 
            </para>

            <para>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/oess_admin_workgroups.png" width="400"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
            
            </para>
            
            <para>
                There is one special workgroup: "OSCARS IDC". Similar to the "OSCARS" user described in the "Users" section, this is
                the workgroup that all remotely provisioned circuits will be associated with. This workgroup is not created by default 
                so it will need to be if you are planning to use interdomain aspects and the OSCARS user will need to be a part of it as
                well as any ports that you would like it to be able to provision to.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        
    </chapter>
    
    <chapter>
        <title>User Interface</title>

        <para>
            The user interface of OESS is designed to allow users to quickly and easily provision circuits across the Openflow network to meet their needs. 
            It also provides a means to interact with OSCARS to provision interdomain circuits, or circuits that span multiple networks. 
        </para>
        
        <para> 
            When a user that has been properly configured and is part of a workgroup goes to the
            OESS home page and selects which workgroup they would like to work in, they will be
            presented with a page like the following: 

        </para>
        
        <para>
            <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/oess_workgroups_home.png" width="400"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
            
        </para>
        
        <para>
            From this page, users can select an existing active circuit from the table provided to see up to date network statistics as well as being able to
            edit or remove the circuit. New circuits can also be created by clicking the "New Circuit" button.
        </para>
        
        <sect1>
            <title>New Circuit</title>
            <para> The first step in creating a new circuit is to provide the OESS software with
                some basic details about the circuit. When these have been filled out, click the Proceed to Step 2 button.
              
            </para>
            
            <para>            
                <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/oess_new_circuit_details.png" width="400"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
                
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <table>
                    <title>Details</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Description </entry>
                                <entry> The human readable description for this circuit. It has no
                                    special meaning outside of uniquely identifying it to users.
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Reserved Bandwidth</entry>
                                <entry> **Not supported in Openflow 1.0** The amount of bandwidth
                                    that circuit created will be guarenteed to have access to.
                                    Currently this does nothing with local Openflow domain circuits,
                                    however it will be passed to an OSCARS instance for doing
                                    interdomain circuits. </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Tagging</entry>
                                <entry> **Q-in-Q not supported in Openflow 1.0** The type of circuit
                                    to create. In Point to Point the ingress and egress point match
                                    1 tag and output 1 tag. For interdomain circuits, this must be
                                    Point to Point. </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Type of Circuit</entry>
                                <entry> Whether this circuit is only on the local domain or is an
                                    interdomain circuit. Please note that currently when creating an
                                    interdomain circuit it will be put into the OSCARS IDC special
                                    workgroup since the request will ultimately wind up coming from
                                    an OSCARS instance. </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </para>
        </sect1>
        
        
        <sect1>
            <title>Endpoints</title>
            <para>
                This section will behave a little differently depending on whether Interdomain or Local Domain was selected during the details component. The purpose of either,
                however, is to choose where the circuit will begin and terminate. In the local domain greater than two endpoints are supported, though not fully recommended due to limitations
                on certain switches. In interdomain, you must have exactly two endpoints.
            </para>
            
            <para> 
                To get started in Local Domain, you will see the interactive map of your network.
                Choose endpoints by first clicking the node you want to terminate on and then the
                port from the list provided. If there are no ports available, it is possible that
                your workgroup does not have access to any ports on this device. This will need to
                be configured in the admin interface by someone with the appropriate authentication.
                Once you have selected the interface you will be prompted to enter a VLAN tag for
                traffic at this end, or you may uncheck the box to allow untagged traffic. 
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/oess_new_circuit_endpoints_local.png" width="400"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
            </para>

            <para>
                Repeat this process for any additional endpoints. If you make a mistake or decide to change an endpoint, you may
                delete it from the Endpoints table by clicking the "Delete" button next to the appropriate entry.

            </para>

            <para> 
                When doing Interdomain circuits, the OESS software must first query the Topology
                service to get a listing of all the endpoints that are available. This may take
                several seconds depending on the complexity of the total topology in the service.
                When it has finished you will be presented with a tree view of all the networks.
                Expanding a network will show you all of the edge ports available. Selecting an edge
                port will prompt you for a desired tag exactly the same as the Local Domain section.
                You must choose exactly two endpoints. 
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/oess_new_circuit_endpoints_remote.png" width="400"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
            
            </para>

        </sect1>
        
        <sect1>
            <title>Primary Path</title>
            <para>
                ** This section is only relevant to Local Domain circuits.**
            </para>
            
            <para> 
                The Primary Path section lets you pick the path of the circuit by clicking on
                links between nodes. The software can also choose a path for you if you click the
                "Suggest Shortest Path" button. In the case of an intranode circuit, an empty path
                is allowable. In any other case, the path must connect all the endpoints.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/oess_new_circuit_primary.png" width="400" />
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>

            </para>

        </sect1>
        
        <sect1>
            <title>Backup Path</title>
            <para>
                ** This section is only relevant to Local Domain circuits.**
            </para>
            
            <para> 
                The Backup Path section lets you pick the backup path for a circuit by clicking
                on links between nodes. In the event of a failure along the primary path, the
                software will reprovision the circuit along the backup path. The software can also
                choose a backup path for you if you click the "Suggest Shortest Path" button. A
                backup path is optional and no backup may be chosen if so desired. 
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/oess_new_circuit_backup.png" width="400" />
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
            
            </para>
                                   
        </sect1>
        
        <sect1>
            <title>Scheduling</title>
            <para> 
                The Scheduling section lets you choose when the provisioning and removal of this
                circuit will happen. The defaults are "Now" for provisiong and "Never" for removal,
                simply meaning that the software will not automatically remove it at a given date
                but it can be removed manually at any time. If you would like to have either or both
                of these actions happen at a later time, choose the "Later" option which will reveal
                a calendar to select the day and a time selector for the time. Please note that it is possible
                for scheduled actions to fail if the conditions under which they were scheduled have 
                changed significantly, such as the removal of a node.
            </para>
            <para>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/oess_new_circuit_scheduling.png" width="400" />
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
            
            </para>
        </sect1>
        
        <sect1>
            <title>Provisioning</title>
            <para>
                The Provisioning section is essentially a summary of the preceeding sections where you may
                examine all the choices made before actually asking the software to make changes to the network.
                As with the Endpoints section, the behavior here is slightly different depending on whether
                you are provisioning a local circuit or an interdomain one.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                In Local Domain mode, clicking the "Submit Circuit Request" button will fire off a request to the OESS software
                backend to provision or schedule the circuit. You should get a notification of the outcome of this action very quickly.
                If the action was to provision the circuit now and the provisioning was successful, you will be redirected to the active
                circuit details page where you can view traffic or make any edits just as if you had selected the circuit
                from the workgroup home page.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                In Interdomain mode, clicking the "Submit Circuit Request" button will send a request to the OSCARS instance to begin
                provisioning an interdomain circuit. During this time you will see a popup that shows the current status in OSCARS of your
                circuit. The time for OSCARS to complete can vary greatly depending on the complexity of the circuit, such as how many
                domains it passes through, as well as how complex its total topology is. Once the circuit has provisioned successfully, you
                will be redirected to the active circuit details page.
            </para>
            
        </sect1>
        
        <sect1>
            <title>Circuit Details</title>
            <para> The Circuit Details section shows up to date information about an active circuit.
                The network map in the bottom left shows current path information which is updated
                periodically, meaning that if a network event happens and a circuit reprovisions
                across a backup path it will be reflected here. Additionally there will be a live
                updating graph showing traffic across this circuit. From here you can opt to edit
                the circuit or remove it. 
                
            </para>
            <para>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/oess_circuit_details.png" width="400" />
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
            </para>

        </sect1>
        
    </chapter>
    
</book>
    
    
